Juan Ibiapina

juanibiapina@gmail.com Berlin, Germany

About me

I have 14 years of experience developing software professionally. I have worked in many different layers of software development, including backend, frontend, mobile and infrastructure. I advocate code quality, readability and maintainability. Tests are part of my development practices, along with TDD and refactoring. I'm confident working with small and fast delivery, continuous integration and many agile ideas. I also have experience designing distributed services, microservices and REST APIs. I'm a big fan of observability.

I like environments where I can grow, surrounded by smart and interesting people. I like to work with respectful, open-minded people who care about their systems, tools and code.

I love to code! I'm a terminal and neovim user. I often learn new programming languages, frameworks and technologies in my free time. I have experimented with many programming languages including SML, Python, Ruby, Haskell, Scala, Go, Rust, Racket, Bash, Clojure, IO, Javascript, Typescript and many others. I even designed my own language marco. I always have at least one active coding side project. You can find more details about personal projects, passions and open source on my Github Profile and my blog

I'm also a game, music and climbing enthusiast.

Experience

Principal Software Developer at Babbel

August 2017 - present

As a Principal at Babbel, I work in the Content Platform team, supporting the learning content CMS and related content distribution APIs for all our internal clients (mainly web and mobile, but also other backends and data). I design or help design cross-team content related initiatives, always striving for small deliverables that bring value to users and allow teams to work independently.

Previous achievements: - Designed content APIs for current and future company initiatives, focusing on changeability. - Actively drove or participated in many topics on our service extraction initiative. - Helped improve development, testing, dependency management, infrastructure and interviewing practices. - I was a major contributor to the migration of user's vocabulary from MySql to DynamoDB. - Contributed to Babbel's engineering strategy, helping teams become more autonomous. - Spread knowledge about content distribution and overall architecture through documentation and workshops. - Mentored developers from Junior to Senior.

Technologies:

- Ruby, Typescript and Go
- Rails, React
- Terraform
- AWS Lambda, DynamoDB, Cloudwatch and many other services

Senior Full-Stack Software Developer at Movinga

Feb 2017 - August 2017

I joined a team of full-stack developers at Movinga and immediately started working on a microservice and its three client applications. I was also responsible for starting a couple of frontend applications from scratch. Later we extracted a pricing microservice from the main legacy code in order to improve deployment times, frequency (from once every two weeks to 10 times a day) and provide better insights about our prices.

Technologies:

- Ruby, Javascript
- Grape, React, Redux and other supporting libraries for both frontend and backend
- · AWS, Docker

Senior Software Developer at Globo.com

May 2015 - Jan 2017

I joined Globo.com to work on the web media platform team. Our team was responsible for receiving and encoding videos to be prepared for internet delivery. We worked on a system that provided both an UI and an API for uploading videos and metadata. This system was distributed in more than 50 locations across Brazil, gathering and processing videos from all partners. We processed more than 2.5TB of videos on a weekly basis, accounting for more than a thousand hours of content.

Accomplishments:

- Designed a content protection microservice that integrates with 3 third party APIs
- Participated on hiring interviews for most people hired in the Porto Alegre office
- Started an observability initiative to gather video encoding metrics and better understand our system
- Helped shape the office culture
- Mentored less experienced developers

Technologies:

- Ruby, Javascript and Coffeescript
- · Rails and Backbone
- Ffmpeg and x264
- Mongo and Redis

Senior Software Developer at Bearch, Inc.

November 2014 - April 2015 (6 months)

We developed an anonymous social network. The whole team worked with all parts of the development, so I had the opportunity to work with a Go backend hosted on Google App Engine, an Android and an iOS application. All of these technologies were new to me.

Accomplishments:

- Shipped a huge amount of features in very little time due to our experimental nature
- Created a pipeline for building and deploying android and iOS apps to their respective stores, improving the testing and release cycles
- Created a camera for Android that worked on more devices than the Whatsapp Camera at the time
- Worked daily with unknown technologies and new challenges

Technologies:

- · Go on Google App Engine
- Javascript with Angular
- · Android with Java
- iOS with Objective C

Software Developer at e-Core

March 2013 - November 2014 (1 year 9 months)

We developed a single page application for a remote client in New York. I was hired not only because I knew some of the technologies involved but also because I was willing to learn the ones I didn't know. This was a project that could change very fast.

Accomplishments:

- Automated the deployment process and reduced the total time from 2 hours down to 160 seconds.
- Helped migrate a legacy application from Grails to Rails
- Experimented with virtual machines, docker and several deployment strategies

Technologies:

- Ruby, Javascript, Coffeescript
- Rails, Knockout.js
- Groovy with Grails
- Puppet, Chef
- Mongo, Postgres, Redis, Solr
- VirtualBox, Docker
- Nginx

Software Developer at Codeminer42

July 2012 - February 2013 (8 months)

We developed systems for startups. It was my first experience with Rails, but also included frontend development. Since each developer was responsible for managing a whole project, our responsibilities involved coding, creating interfaces, thinking about user experience, negotiating with clients, managing infrastructure and deployment, etc.

I was one of the first people to be hired on our branch of the company, so I had the opportunity to help build the culture we wanted. I learned a lot from the experience and it helped shape some of my future career goals.

Accomplishments:

- Migrated an application from rails 2 to rails 4
- Helped shape the office culture
- Developed a project from conception to delivery

Technologies:

- · Ruby, Javascript
- Postgres

Development Consultant at ThoughtWorks

January 2011 - June 2012 (1 year 6 months)

Consisted mainly of consulting and web development for the retail industry, with daily client facing situations. I worked mostly on maintaining and developing new features for a large legacy Java code base. Teams were distributed across Brazil, India and the US.

This was my first contact with agile practices. I have learned much from it, including the importance of pair programming, TDD and Continuous Integration. I had a mentor that helped me build most of my ideas about development.

Accomplishments:

- Started an initiative to improve development and feedback cycles
- Introduced Javascript unit tests into the project
- Started a culture of looking into build status
- Extended the development tools, greatly improving development speed and team motivation
- Acquired the trust of some of the clients, making our work much easier
- Participated on ThoughtWorks University, which changed my life
- Started learning about interviewing candidates

Technologies:

- Java and Spring
- Javascript
- Ruby for integration tests

Education

Universidade Federal do Piauí (UFPI)

Bachelor of Science (BS), Computer Science, 2004 - 2007

Languages

- Portuguese (Native)
- English (Fluent)